<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian laver. Or, a discourse opening the nature of participation with, and demonstrating the necessity of purification by Christ By T. Cruso.</title>
            <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R225717</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896967</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132881</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81101)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2465:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian laver. Or, a discourse opening the nature of participation with, and demonstrating the necessity of purification by Christ By T. Cruso.</title>
                  <author>Cruso, Timothy, 1656?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 80, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.R. for J. Salusbury at the Rising Sun in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a three final advertisement leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Knowableness --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Purity, Ritual --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spiritual life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132881:1"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIAN LAVER. OR, A DISCOURSE Opening The Nature of <hi>Participation</hi> with, And Demonſtrating The Neceſſity of <hi>Purification</hi> by CHRIST. By <hi>T. CR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SO.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOB 9.30, 31.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If I waſh my ſelf with Snow-water, and make my hands never ſo clean;</p>
               <p>Yet ſhalt thou plunge me in the Ditch, and my own Cloathes ſhall abhor me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>I. Salusbury</hi> at the <hi>Riſing <hi>Sun</hi>
               </hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:132881:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132881:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>two</hi> following <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> (which have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd little alteration, more than by being caſt into the form of <hi>one</hi> continued <hi>Diſcourſe</hi>) were lately <hi>preach'd</hi> in the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of my ordinary fixed work among thoſe whom I am called eſpecially to Miniſter to, and afterwards <hi>tranſcrib'd</hi> for the ſatisfaction and ſervice of ſome particular Friends, that heard them, whoſe deſires in any
<pb facs="tcp:132881:3"/>ſuch caſe, I acknowledge my ſelf upon many accounts, obliged to fulfil; And if it were proper here to publiſh their kindneſs, or to expreſs my own juſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude at large, I might very eaſily be excus'd, by all Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous perſons, for <hi>ſending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad</hi> theſe Papers, at their requeſt, into the World; but to thoſe who will not admit <hi>this</hi> Apology, I ſhall offer <hi>none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had immediately before the preaching of this, endeavour'd the opening of <hi>Another</hi> Subject, which I thought <hi>preparatory</hi> to it, from thoſe words of <hi>Eliphaz, What is man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 15.14.</note> 
               <hi>that he ſhould be clean?</hi> &amp;c. which I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the true reaſon, why
<pb facs="tcp:132881:3"/>that Great point of the <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Human Nature</hi> is ſearcht into ſo little here. Whoſoever are <hi>Strangers</hi> or <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries</hi> to ſuch Doctrine, they are manifeſtly ſo unacquainted with, and oppoſite to the <hi>whole Goſpel</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, that I deſpair of their getting any good by my management of this Text; for as they that believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a <hi>ſound</hi> and healthful ſtate,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 12.</note> conclude that they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Generation</hi> who are already <hi>pure in their own Eyes,</hi> will take no thought about being <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from their filthineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The main ſubſtance of our <hi>Religion</hi> as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (which
<pb facs="tcp:132881:4"/>
               <hi>Lapſed</hi> Creatures, I am ſure, are chiefly concerned to regard) is reducible to theſe <hi>two Heads:</hi> Our <hi>defilement by Adam,</hi> and our <hi>cleanſing by Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> according as men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove in the knowledge of theſe things, they are like to <hi>hold faſt,</hi> or let go, the <hi>Myſtery of Faith;</hi> for I muſt profeſs, that I cannot underſtand, what <hi>their</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity does amount to, who either <hi>deny</hi> or <hi>deprave</hi> the moſt fundamental Articles. It is not a ſtedfaſt aſſertion of the <hi>Principles,</hi> or ſtrict perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the <hi>Duties,</hi> of <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Religion,</hi> which will make any amends for our <hi>Ignorance,</hi> or <hi>Errour</hi> here; we that live
<pb facs="tcp:132881:4"/>in ſuch an Age and Place, muſt not think it enough, to go as far in our <hi>practiſe,</hi> or riſe as high in our <hi>belief,</hi> as the <hi>Heathens</hi> did; but it will be matter of ſhame and condemnation to us, if having ſo much greater <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries,</hi> and better <hi>Helps,</hi> we ſhould at moſt be onely found to Equal their <hi>Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is evident enough, that the <hi>Rotten Notions</hi> of many, and the <hi>Filthy Lewdneſs</hi> of the moſt, call for ſomewhat of this kind, for their Conviction and Awakening; but I have no ſuch fond opinion of <hi>this</hi> poor perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, as to imagine, that it
<pb facs="tcp:132881:5"/>will contribute very much to ſo uſeful and valuable Ends; unleſs God ſhould exerciſe the like <hi>Prerogative of Grace,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing of his Arm <hi>by</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible worm, as in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of his Will <hi>to</hi> unskilful Babes,<note place="margin">Luk. 10.21.</note> when the <hi>Wiſe and Prudent</hi> are left with a Viel upon their Minds. If he pleaſe to make uſe of the vileſt Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and thoſe which are <hi>leaſt eſteemed,</hi> he can put a <hi>more abundant honour</hi> upon them by his efficacious Preſence; and what he is <hi>able</hi> to do, I offer up my earneſt Prayers to him (craving aſſiſtance in it from others) that he <hi>may
<pb facs="tcp:132881:5"/>now</hi> do, <hi>making perfect</hi> his own <hi>ſtrength in the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the moſt unworthy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour.</p>
            <p>And I conclude, with ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying my <hi>Hearts Deſire,</hi> that every Reader, whom Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence directs to caſt his Eye upon theſe Lines, may have ſome cauſe to Bleſs God for them, and to <hi>report that God was in them of a truth:</hi> which, I wiſh, may appear in <hi>all,</hi> as well as in <hi>my ſelf,</hi> by a daily <hi>clearer diſcerning</hi> of our own <hi>Spots,</hi> a more <hi>humble walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> with God, a more <hi>entire Confidence</hi> in Chriſt, and
<pb facs="tcp:132881:6"/>more <hi>vigorous endeavours</hi> after a perfect Conformity to his perfect Holineſs.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Feb. 12. 1689/90.</hi>
               </date>
               <signed>T. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132881:6"/>
            <head>The CHRISTIAN LAVER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN 13.8. Latter Part.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—Jeſus anſwered him, If I waſh thee not, thou haſt no part with me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THe beginning of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gives us an account of that eminently <hi>Condeſcending Act</hi> of Chriſt in waſhing the feet of his Diſciples. The exact and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular time, <hi>when</hi> this was done, is much diſputed. 'Tis ſaid, (<hi>ver.</hi> 2.) <hi>Supper being ended—,</hi> and (<hi>ver.</hi> 4.) <hi>He roſe from Supper, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132881:7"/>laid aſide his garments, and took a towel,</hi> &amp;c. The great Queſtion is, what this <hi>Supper</hi> was.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some, (nay indeed the Generality) do think, that it was the <hi>Paſchal</hi> Supper; the <hi>fourth</hi> and laſt which our Bleſſed Lord ever kept with his Diſciples, after which the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> was immediately inſtituted.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others, (among whom prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the Learned Dr. <hi>Light-foot</hi>) think that it was a <hi>common</hi> Ordinary Supper, two dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Feaſt of the Paſſeover;<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>26.2,</hi> &amp;c.</note> the ſame with that at <hi>Bethany</hi> in the houſe of <hi>Simon the Leper</hi> Several Arguments are brought to overthrow the former opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in favour of this. As 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſaid expreſly here, <hi>v.</hi> 1. that it was <hi>before the Feaſt of the Paſſeover.</hi> 2. Becauſe when our Lord bid <hi>Judas to do quickly what he did,</hi> ſome of the Diſciples
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:132881:7"/>thought, that he was to <hi>provide things againſt the Feaſt,</hi> v. 29. which implyes, that the Feaſt was not yet come. But I mention no more.</p>
            <p>Whenſoever this Act was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, the <hi>moving Cauſe</hi> of it is intimated both v. 1. and 3. Chriſt was <hi>departing out of the World,</hi> and <hi>going to God.</hi> He was now exercis'd in the thoughts of his approaching Death, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Glory, and being conſtant and immutable in his Affections to <hi>his own.</hi> he was reſoly'd to give them before he ſuffer'd, ſuch a <hi>ſenſible proof</hi> of his <hi>Love,</hi> as he could not give after he came to Heaven.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papiſts</hi> lay much ſtreſs upon <hi>ver.</hi> 6. in arguing for the <hi>precedency</hi> of their <hi>ſuppoſed Biſhop; Then cometh he to Simon Peter,</hi> &amp;c. but there is nothing of weight or force in this; what if (as the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132881:8"/>forenamed Reverend Author conjectures)<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>J. Lightfoot</hi> Hor. Hebr. in Joh.</note> our Lord onely waſht the feet of two or three of the Diſciples, which was enough to ſhow his deſign, as much as if he had waſht them all? <hi>Peter James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were diſtinguiſh ſometimes from the reſt by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Chriſts greateſt priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; perhaps ſo it might be it this action too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter</hi> indeed is the <hi>onely</hi> perſon here ſpoken of, but all that is ſaid concerning him upon this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is not to his commendation His <hi>modeſt</hi> Queſtion at the firſt might be well enough excus'd <hi>Lord, doſt thou waſh my fect?</hi> He might very well admire that Chriſt ſhould ſtoop ſo much be low himſelf: And therefore our Lord does <hi>calmly</hi> admoniſh him <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>What I do, thou knoweſ not now, but thou ſhalt know here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. q. d.</hi> There is ſomewhat
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132881:8"/>more in it, than the bare act of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, which thou doſt not at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſee into; but when the Spirit is poured out, thy underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall be more enlighten'd in this and other miſteries. One would think that <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould have been ſatisfied with this, and readily complyed; as <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> is ſaid to <hi>forbid</hi> Chriſt at firſt, when he <hi>came to be baptized fo him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.14, 15.</note> but when he heard Chriſt's anſwer, he <hi>ſuffered him.</hi> This Apoſtle (on the contrary) does peremptorily oppoſe, <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Thou ſhalt never waſh my feet.</hi> q. d. I will not yeild or conſent to it.</p>
            <p>From whence, by the way might be noted, that <hi>Men may have much ſeeming humility in the matters of God, which yet is very abſurd and prepoſterous, ariſing meerly from carnal reaſon. Peter</hi> once before ran into this <hi>Extreme;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk, 5.8.</note> when <hi>he fell down at Jeſus his knees
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132881:9"/>Saying, depart from me, oh Lord, for I am a ſinful man;</hi> which was in effect, to wiſh the greateſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity to himſelf that could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal him. How fatal would it have been, if our Lord had grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that requeſt, and baniſht him out of his ſociety! or if <hi>Peter's</hi> word had ſtood in the preſent caſe! but Chriſt lets him ſee in his Reply to this raſh reſolution, the <hi>danger</hi> of ſuch a refuſal, <hi>If I waſh thee not, thou haſt no part with me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of the words, three <hi>Queſtions</hi> ſhould be breifly Diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſt. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> What was the <hi>ſcope</hi> and meaning of our Saviour in this Act of <hi>waſhing his Diſciples feet? Anſw.</hi> He did not inſtitute this as a <hi>ſtanding Ceremony,</hi> (though it be kept up under ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the <hi>Roman Church</hi>) but he ſeems to have done it at that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132881:9"/>time upon ſome or all of theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As an <hi>inſtance</hi> of his Great <hi>Lowlineſs of mind,</hi> which they were to <hi>imitate</hi> him in. So he preſſes it, v. 14, 15. <hi>If I your Lord and Maſter have waſhed your feet; you alſo</hi> (who are fellow ſervants) <hi>ought to waſh one another's feet; For I have given you an Example,</hi> &amp;c. This was one of the <hi>mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ext offices</hi> and employments, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways performed by <hi>Inferiours</hi> to ſuperiours, but never by <hi>ſuperiours</hi> to <hi>Inferiours;</hi> as <hi>Abigal</hi> ſaid of her ſelf with repect to <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25.41.</note> 
               <hi>Let thine Handmaid be a ſervant to waſh the feet of the ſervants of my Lord.</hi> Therefore this was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per teſtimony of Chriſt's remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſelf-abaſement.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It might <hi>preſignify</hi> to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that <hi>Baptiſm of blood</hi> which they were to undergo in confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to him. The <hi>ointment</hi> which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132881:10"/>was <hi>poured on his body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26.12.</note> he inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted as <hi>done for his burial;</hi> ſo this waſhing of their feetwas a kind of Preparative to their being <hi>drencht</hi> in <hi>deeper ſufferings.</hi> Chriſt had told <hi>James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> that they ſhould be <hi>baptized with the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 10.39.</note> 
               <hi>which he was baptized with.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If it were, as ſome ſuppoſe, a little <hi>before the Inſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Lords ſupper,</hi> it ſhews the <hi>Purity</hi> which is required in thoſe who celebrate that ordinance, and the <hi>pains</hi> which ſhould be taken in order to it.<note place="margin">Exod. 12.15.</note> Upon the <hi>firſt day of the Paſſover,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> were commanded to <hi>put away leaven out of their Houſes:</hi> accordingly if we would <hi>keep this feaſt</hi> aright,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.7, 8.</note> which comes in the room of the Paſſover, we muſt <hi>firſt purge out the old Leaven.</hi> Therefore this waſhing might be a very ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable act.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It did fitly <hi>repreſent</hi> that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132881:10"/>
               <hi>Inward Cleanſing</hi> which is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to every one's Salvation; and this is that which our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our principally aim'd at. The waſhing of the feet (like the many <hi>Ceremonial waſhings</hi> under the Law) was but a <hi>Figure</hi> of the <hi>puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the ſoul,</hi> whereing his main work, as Redeemer, did conſiſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> why does our Lord paſſe ſo <hi>ſevere</hi> a ſentence upon <hi>Peter,</hi> as that he ſhould <hi>have no part with him, meerly upon the ſuppoſition</hi> of his <hi>denying</hi> to be <hi>waſht by him?</hi> does ſo ſmall a crime (ſpringing alſo from a ſenſe of unworthineſs) call for ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy a puniſhment? <hi>Anſw.</hi> In two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Contempt of any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> of Chriſt (how <hi>little</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it may Appear to be) <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves</hi> that the Contemner ſhould be <hi>excluded from Chriſt.</hi> All wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful diſobedience to our Lord's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132881:11"/>will is deſtructive, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in, and admitts of no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe. <hi>To ſuſpend our practiſe</hi> of any duty, till we <hi>underſtand the reaſon</hi> of the Precept, is indeed worthy of an everlaſting Hell.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>weight of the threatening</hi> lyes upon that which is <hi>intended</hi> by this waſhing; q. d. unleſs I purge thee <hi>Peter,</hi> from thoſe <hi>remaining dregs</hi> of Corruption which are about thee, thou wilt be cut off from having any thing to do with me. <hi>Peter</hi> had diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great deal of weakneſs and ſin <hi>before;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.22, 23.</note> as when he took upon him <hi>Satan's office,</hi> and rebuk't his Maſter for ſpeaking of his <hi>Paſſion,</hi> inſomuch that Chriſt told him, <hi>Thou ſavoureſt not the things of God, but of men.</hi> There was as great deal more ſin which <hi>this Apoſtle</hi> betrayed <hi>afterwards;</hi> ſuch as,<note place="margin">Chap. 26.33.</note> Too good an <hi>eſteem of</hi> and too much <hi>confidence in</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:132881:11"/>
               <hi>(Though all men be offended, yet I never will)</hi> ſhameful <hi>drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs</hi> and ſloth; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>40,</label> 
               <hi>(Could ye not watch with me one hour?)</hi> Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and <hi>inconſiderate zeal;</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>51</label> (wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>Malchus's ear ſtruck off</hi> by his <hi>ſword.</hi>) <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>70,</label> 
               <hi>Exceſſive fear</hi> and cowardiſe, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>72,</label> which plunged him unto thoſe repeated <hi>denials</hi> and <hi>Abjurations</hi> of this Lord. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>74</label> All theſe evils, which yet ſtuck to <hi>Peter,</hi> he needed to have waſht away, that he might not be <hi>accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from Chriſt</hi> for ever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Queſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> It may be alſo En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, whether Chriſt's <hi>waſhing of Peter</hi> would ſufficiently ſecure <hi>Peter's partaking with</hi> Chriſt? our Lord ſays here, <hi>If I waſh thee not,</hi> &amp;c. the Queſtion is, whether it hold on the other ſide, that <hi>If I waſh thee, thou haſt a part with me? Anſw.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:132881:12"/>
            <p n="1">1 If we underſtand it of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal waſhing</hi> onely, it muſt be affirmed, that any of the Diſciples, notwithſtanding that, might have been ſhut out from having any fellowſhip with Chriſt. The <hi>putting away of the filth of the fleſh</hi> will not ſave the ſoul from Hell. <hi>Judas</hi> might have his feet waſht, and yet his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicience</hi> continue <hi>defiled.</hi> This of it ſelf, would have ſignifyed no more,<note place="margin">Luke 13.26.</note> than <hi>Eating and drinking in Chriſt's preſence,</hi> which will En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title no <hi>worker of Iniquity</hi> to the kingdom of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If we underſtand it of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Purification,</hi> (as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed eſpecially to be underſtood) this is always accompanied with a ſaving intereſt in Chriſt If we can prove that He hath <hi>cleanſed us,</hi> we have evidence enough, that He is <hi>ours.</hi> His <hi>Blood</hi> is never ſpent upon <hi>Caſt-awayes</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:132881:12"/>like <hi>water</hi> vainly <hi>ſpilt upon the ground.</hi> We need no more to certifie our <hi>propriety in</hi> him, than the receiving of ſuch a <hi>benefit from</hi> him. Therefore the <hi>Reverſe</hi> of what our Saviour here ſays, is alſo true.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Obſervation</hi> which I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to inſiſt on, is this, that <hi>It is abſolutely neceſſary,</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Doct.</note> 
               <hi>that we ſhould be waſht by Chriſt, in order to our being partakers with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Method</hi> which I intend in the handling of this Point, is.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> To ſhew, what it is to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with Chriſt.</item>
               <item>II. How are we waſhed by him.</item>
               <item>III. Why is there ſuch a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of this waſhing.</item>
               <item>IV. To Apply it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To explain, what it is to <hi>have a part with</hi> Chriſt. <hi>Anſw.</hi> In general, it may bear the ſame
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132881:13"/>ſenſe, as <hi>partaking of</hi> him; which was an encouragement that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> laid before the <hi>converted Hebrews.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.14</note> And that way of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is uſual both in the old and new Teſtament. The <hi>two tribes and half</hi> were afraid, leſt the children of the <hi>other Tribes</hi> ſhould ſay to <hi>theirs</hi> in the time to come,<note place="margin">Joſh. 22.27.</note> 
               <hi>ye have no part in the Lord. Peter</hi> tells <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> who would have bought the <hi>Gift of the Holy Ghost</hi> with money, <hi>Thou haſt nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part nor let in this matter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 8.21.</note> So, 'tis threaten'd at the cloſe of the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 22.19.</note> that if any man ſhould take away from the words of the book of that propheſy, God would <hi>take away his part out of the book of life, and the holy City</hi> &amp;c. All theſe paſſages, though upon different occaſions, help to illuſtrate the phraſe here. 'Tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plain, that it muſt not be taken in ſo <hi>groſſe</hi> a ſenſe, as if our Lord
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132881:13"/>Jeſus were <hi>divided</hi> and <hi>ſhar'd</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong believers, as his <hi>Garments</hi> were taken and <hi>parted</hi> among the Souldiers; It is an <hi>whole</hi> and entire Saviour which is given to <hi>Every one; He</hi> and <hi>all</hi> that belongs to him, Is made ours, <hi>if any thing</hi> of his be ours. All the <hi>members</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive <hi>aſmuch</hi> from this Head, as if there were but one member for this <hi>Head</hi> to communicate to.</p>
            <p>If we have <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> from him, we have <hi>Holineſs</hi> alſo; if we have <hi>Grace,</hi> we ſhall have <hi>Glory;</hi> if we are <hi>buried with him,</hi> we ſhall be <hi>quicken'd with him;</hi> if we are <hi>planted into his death,</hi> we ſhall <hi>reap the fruits of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection</hi> to. To <hi>partake of Chriſt</hi> therefore, is tob e <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> of, or <hi>entitled</hi> too, all that Chriſt <hi>is</hi> or <hi>hath,</hi> which is communicable. 'Tis no <hi>ſmall thing in it ſelf,</hi> it ought not to be a ſmall thing <hi>with us.</hi> To have the Bleſſed Jeſus,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132881:14"/>and his <hi>purchaſe,</hi> for our <hi>portion,</hi> is more than to be Lords of the world, or to have Empires and Kingdoms at command. A Title to Chriſt gives a <hi>right</hi> to every thing elſe that's worth enjoying; a right to the <hi>favour</hi> of God, to all the <hi>Promiſes</hi> of God, a right to <hi>Sacraments,</hi> the beſt right to <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Comforts,</hi> and an undoubted right to <hi>heaven</hi> it ſelf. But more particularly, To <hi>have part with</hi> Chriſt comprehends theſe five things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion to his perſon.</hi> They that have no part <hi>with</hi> Chriſt, are not part <hi>of</hi> him.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.17.</note> Whereas, to be <hi>joyned to the Lord</hi> himſelf is the great priviledge of a Chriſtian; as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaid to that <hi>Cori-thian</hi> Church, <hi>now ye are the body of Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">chap. 12.27.</note> 
               <hi>and members in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Being in</hi> Chriſt, is primari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſed, before there can be a <hi>participation of</hi> him: <hi>i.e.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:132881:14"/>in him, not by <hi>viſible profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> within the pale of the Church, as <hi>Souldiers</hi> in an <hi>Army,</hi> but as <hi>Branches</hi> in a <hi>vine,</hi> by <hi>real and vital conjunction.</hi> That (&amp; that onely) which ſeparates from the <hi>perſon</hi> of Chriſt, does ſtrip us of all his <hi>benefits.</hi> If we are not united to <hi>him,</hi> we can claim no ſhare in any thing that's <hi>his.</hi> They who talk againſt this union (of which they have no <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> knowledge) as a fiction, or an abſurdity, do in effect de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the <hi>bleſſeings</hi> of the Goſpel and <hi>fruits</hi> of Chriſt's mediation. <hi>Without him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John. 15.5.</note> (i.e. without a <hi>living Implantation</hi> into him) we <hi>can do</hi> or receive <hi>nothing.</hi> The Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous miſtery of Chriſt's <hi>Incarnation</hi> lyes in the taking of <hi>our nature</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to union with the <hi>divine nature</hi> in <hi>one perſon,</hi> i.e. in himſelf, as God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: the myſtery of our <hi>Spiritual Incorporation</hi> with Chriſt, lyes in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:132881:15"/>uniting the <hi>perſons of Beleivers</hi> with the <hi>perſon of Chriſt.</hi> So that the <hi>Head</hi> and the <hi>members</hi> make but <hi>one Body; we</hi> are <hi>compleat in him,</hi> who are the members; <hi>he</hi> as an Head,<note place="margin">Eph. 1.23.</note> is <hi>not compleat without us.</hi> As he <hi>fills all in all</hi> with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to the Church is his <hi>Full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> To <hi>have a part with</hi> Chriſt, implies <hi>Communion with him</hi> in the honour and priviledge of <hi>Sonſhip.</hi> Not that the ſame <hi>filial relation</hi> to God the <hi>Father</hi> can be put upon Creatures which is <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall</hi> to him, but <hi>ſomething like</hi> it, is allowed and indulg'd to us. We cannot be the <hi>Children of God</hi> by <hi>nature,</hi> as Chriſt is, but we may be advanc't into <hi>ſuch</hi> a Relation by <hi>Grace.</hi> Chriſt was <hi>begotten</hi> of God from <hi>everlasting,</hi> we may be <hi>Adopted</hi> in <hi>time.</hi> His Eternal <hi>Generation</hi> made him,<note place="margin">Gala. 3.26.</note> a Son: <hi>by faith in him,</hi> we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:132881:15"/>become <hi>Children</hi> alſo. The ſtanding <hi>Angels</hi> are not the <hi>Sons of God</hi> upon ſo good a <hi>bottom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.26</note> as we are: they are ſuch by <hi>Creation,</hi> we by a <hi>ſpecial Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> they have this title as a <hi>common Grant</hi> from their <hi>maker,</hi> (which <hi>Adam</hi> once had, but after his fall, it was no longer uſefull to him;) we now have it from the <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> bounty of our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. To as many as receive him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>he gives power to become the ſons of God.</hi> All believers are ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites; (though none beſides) The <hi>Spirit of Adoption whereby we cry Abba, Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.</note> is given to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of them. We are all raiſed up to a fellowſhip with Chriſt in this matter of Sonſhip, than which nothing can be more honourable or beneficial to us. The <hi>little ones</hi> of the family are as truly the Children of the Higheſt, as thoſe that are of fuller age, and a larger
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:132881:16"/>growth. It was happy news to all the followers of Chriſt when <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> told them, what ſhe had heard at the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher from his own mouth,<note place="margin">John 20.17.</note> 
               <hi>I aſcend unto my Father, and your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to my God, and your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> it includes an <hi>Intereſt in his perfect performances.</hi> Chriſt was to do all that was <hi>Commanded,</hi> as well as to ſuffer what was <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;</hi> now, what he <hi>did,</hi> as well as what he <hi>ſuffered,</hi> we are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of, if we have any part with Chriſt himſelf. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> aſſures us, that it was the great end of <hi>God's ſending his Son into the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>that the Righteouſneſs of the Law might be fulfilled in us.</hi> He had ſaid before that <hi>there is no Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to them that are in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">verſ. </seg>1</label> they that are become <hi>one</hi> with him, can no more be condemned than <hi>he</hi> now can, but are <hi>juſtified upon the ſame ſcore.</hi> Here, 'tis more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:132881:16"/>diſtinctly explain'd, Chriſt fulfill'd all righteouſneſs <hi>for</hi> us, and ſo the Righteouſneſs of the Law is ſaid to be fulfilled <hi>in</hi> us. (we may obſerve, that 'tis no ſuch <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical</hi> Righteouſneſs, conſiſting in Faith, Repentance and new obedience, which ſome are pleaſed to call the <hi>works of the Goſpel,</hi> as is made uſe of to pervert the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuin Doctrine of <hi>Juſtification;</hi> but <hi>the Righteouſneſs of the Law</hi>) It was <hi>neceſſary</hi> that <hi>ſuch</hi> a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſhould <hi>be fulfill'd;</hi> (one that was <hi>imperfect,</hi> how <hi>ſincere</hi> ſoever, could not ſuffice) it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that <hi>we</hi> ſhould fulfil ſuch a righteouſneſs <hi>in our own perſons,</hi> after we were diſabled by the fall, when the <hi>Law,</hi> as to it's <hi>juſtfying power,</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>weak through</hi> our <hi>fleſh:</hi> God therefore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed that his Son ſhould do this in <hi>our ſtead,</hi> and when he had ſo done, God accepted it <hi>on
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:132881:17"/>our behalf;</hi> and we are therefore <hi>lookt upon</hi> in Chriſt, and for his ſake to be <hi>as juſt</hi> and righteous, <hi>as if we</hi> had done all <hi>our ſelves.</hi> We have the benefit of all that <hi>obedience</hi> which fill'd up and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn'd the <hi>Life of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> it imployes our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſharers</hi> in his Abſolute <hi>victory over all our Spiritual Enemies;</hi> ſin and Satan, death and Hell. This ought to be laid down as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable truth, that Jeſus Chriſt did not overcome theſe Enemies ſo much <hi>for himſelf,</hi> as <hi>for us;</hi> as God, he was not lyable to be <hi>aſſaulted</hi> by them; but as Mediator, he freely and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily <hi>Submitted</hi> to their aſſaults, to ſhew how eaſily and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally he could over power them, and diſarm them from hurting Beleivers. The <hi>Devil</hi> could not have tempted him, <hi>Death</hi> could not have ſeiz'd him, (no, not for ſo ſhort a time, not for the ſmalleſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:132881:17"/>moment) unleſs he had <hi>ſo far</hi> unchain'd <hi>them,</hi> and yielded <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;</hi> but his End was to make his own Victory the more <hi>conſpicuous,</hi> and ours the more <hi>ſecure.</hi> All the <hi>Souldiers</hi> of Chriſt overcome, by vertue of their <hi>Captains</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming; becauſe he baffled our Adverſaries, we cannot be worſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them.<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14, 15.</note> Chriſts <hi>deſtroying of him that had the power of death,</hi> was a <hi>delivering of us from the juſt fear of death.</hi> When the Apoſtle had reckoned up a great many evils which Chriſtians lye open to, he ſays,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note> 
               <hi>In all theſe things we are more than Conquerers through him that loved us. His</hi> Conqueſt is <hi>ours;</hi> the Scripture often inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates this. The ſame Apoſtle makes twice a ſolemn acknowledgment of it;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.57.</note> 
               <hi>Thanks be unto God who giveth us the Victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And again, <hi>Thanks be unto God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>which always
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:132881:18"/>cauſeth us to triumph in Chriſt.</hi> His <hi>bruiſing of the head</hi> of the ſerpent, enables us to <hi>trample</hi> on him too.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> It includes our <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Fellowſhip</hi> with Chriſt <hi>in his Kingdom and Glory.</hi> To <hi>have a part</hi> with him, is finally to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the ſame <hi>reward,</hi> and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate in the happineſs of his <hi>Exalted State.</hi> This is to be (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that lofty Expreſſion) <hi>Joynt Heirs with Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> He him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſays, that the faithful Servant ſhall <hi>enter into the joy of his Lord;</hi> not <hi>another</hi> joy different from his,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.21, 23.</note> but <hi>his</hi> joy, that which he, as <hi>our forerunner,</hi> is entred into already <hi>for us.</hi> He animates and excites us to follow him in this World, by this conſideration relating to the next:<note place="margin">John 12.26.</note> 
               <hi>Where I am, there alſo ſhall my Servant be.</hi> This he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats and confirms afterwards: <hi>I will come again,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14.13.</note> 
               <hi>and receive you to my ſelf,</hi> (not to any <hi>ſeparate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:132881:18"/>Manſion</hi> in my Fathers Houſe, but to my own preſence) <hi>that where I am, there you may be alſo.</hi> The nearer we come to the concluſion of the Bible, the more and greater aſſurances we have of this.<note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>Having a deſire</hi> (ſays <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>to depart, and to be with Chriſt;</hi> this is a proper deſcription of the Nature of the Heavenly felicity. the ſame he gives to his <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians; ſo ſhall we be ever with the Lord;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſs. 4.17.</note> 'tis plain, that he means <hi>that Lord Jeſus, who</hi> (as we read in the foregoing words) <hi>ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from Heaven with a ſhout,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">v. </seg>16</label> and ſnatch up all that ſurvive at his laſt coming, thither. <hi>Timothy</hi> is ſupported under his ſufferings, by this, that we ſhall both <hi>live and reign with Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.11, 12.</note> And the moſt tranſporting paſſage of all, is yet behind;<note place="margin">Revel. 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>To him that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh</hi> (ſays our Lord, in that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:132881:19"/>Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi>) <hi>will I grant to ſit with me in my Throne, even as I,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Herod</hi> ſtretcht very far, and ſhew'd his mighty affection to the <hi>Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Herodias,</hi> when he ſaid, that he would give her, whatever ſhe askt,<note place="margin">Mar. 6.23</note> 
               <hi>to the half of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> Chriſt goes much farther, as his Kingdom is much better; the <hi>whole of it</hi> ſhall be as much <hi>ours his.</hi> He was partaker with us in our <hi>Infirmities</hi> and <hi>Sorrows,</hi> we ſhall be Partners with him in his <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Bleſſedneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> thing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> is to ſhew, How Sinners are <hi>waſht by</hi> Chriſt, that this Propoſition may be fully cleared, <hi>If I waſh thee not,</hi> &amp;c. Anſ. Chriſts <hi>waſhing of us</hi> is <hi>Two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold,</hi> according to the <hi>double</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage which we lye under, of <hi>Guilt</hi> and <hi>Impurity;</hi> the one renders us <hi>obnoxious</hi> to God's <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:132881:19"/>the other makes us <hi>odious</hi> to his <hi>Holineſs.</hi> For the <hi>removal</hi> of both theſe, there muſt be a waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and of <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification;</hi> and both of them are and muſt be <hi>performed</hi> by our Lord Jeſus. As will particularly appear.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> There is a <hi>waſhing of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stification,</hi> which the Holy Ghoſt aſcribes to Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Ye are waſhed—ye are justified in the Name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.11.</note> &amp;c. The ſame <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> who ſays this, ſays indeed likewiſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33.</note> 
               <hi>It is God that juſtfieth;</hi> 'tis properly the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative Act of the <hi>Soveraign Judge,</hi> but he does it <hi>in the name</hi> of his Son (as he is ſaid to <hi>ſend the Spirit in his Sons Name</hi>) <hi>i.e.</hi> upon his Sons Account,<note place="margin">John 14.26.</note> who hath obtained by <hi>his</hi> ſufferings, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of <hi>our</hi> Sins. This is aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:132881:20"/>very often;<note place="margin">1 John 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 1.5.</note> Again, <hi>To him that loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his own Blood;</hi> i.e. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as the foregoing part of that verſe ſhews. Now this <hi>Waſhing</hi> or cleanſing <hi>by his Blood,</hi> is effected, both by the ſhedding, and by the <hi>ſprinkling</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> By the <hi>ſheding of Chriſts Blood</hi> above 1600 years ago, <hi>upon the Croſs,</hi> All Believers were <hi>virtually</hi> and <hi>meritoriouſly</hi> waſht. There was then a <hi>General Expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> made for all their ſins, and <hi>one Sacrifice offered to God,</hi> which would never afterwards need a <hi>Repetition.</hi> There <hi>remains no more Sacrifice now;</hi> the Work was finiſht, and perfected by <hi>that.</hi> Chriſt then <hi>purged our ſins;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> and made way for our <hi>free pardon</hi> by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:132881:20"/>his <hi>full ſatisfaction.</hi> Therefore the Blood of Jeſus (conſidering its <hi>Infinite value</hi>) may well be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as a <hi>Sea</hi> deep enough to <hi>drown</hi> all our guilt in; according to that Promiſe in the <hi>Prophet, Thou wilt caſt all their ſins into the depths of the Sea.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micah 7.19.</note> Chriſt's Blood is to our ſins, as the <hi>Red Sea</hi> was to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> a perpetual <hi>Grave,</hi> from which they can never be <hi>raiſed</hi> again. Now that Blood which ſtifles the <hi>Guilt,</hi> (even in ſo doing) waſhes the <hi>Perſon;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 33.8.</note> 
               <hi>I will cleanſe them</hi> (ſays God) <hi>from all their Iniquity, and I will pardon all their Iniquities. Pardoning</hi> and <hi>cleanſing</hi> are the <hi>ſame thing,</hi> and the <hi>Blood of the Croſs</hi> is the only <hi>conſideration with God</hi> upon which 'tis done. If <hi>that</hi> had not been <hi>pour'd out,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.18.</note> the Dye of <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> and <hi>Crimſon</hi> ſins could never have been turn'd into the white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:132881:21"/>of <hi>Wool</hi> and <hi>Snow. All things by the Law</hi> (ſays the <hi>great Apoſtle</hi>) <hi>are purged with Blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.22.</note> 
               <hi>and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhedding of Blood is no remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> The ſame Method holds un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as before under the <hi>Law;</hi> ſo that there is neither <hi>Real,</hi> nor <hi>Typical,</hi> neither <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial</hi> nor <hi>Spiritual</hi> remiſſion or purgation, but by <hi>Blood ſhed;</hi> Typical and Ceremonial by the <hi>Blood of Calves and Goats,</hi> &amp;c. Real and Spiritual by the <hi>Blood of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> By the <hi>ſprinkling of Christs 'Blood upon the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of every <hi>Believer,</hi> they come to be <hi>actually</hi> waſht. For there muſt be a <hi>particular application</hi> of the Merit of that Blood to every one by <hi>Faith,</hi> or elſe no one can have any advantage by it. We muſt through the operations of Gods Grace <hi>in</hi> and <hi>upon</hi> us, poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively <hi>concur</hi> to the ſprinkling of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:132881:21"/>Chriſts Blood upon our hearts, though the ſhedding of it upon the Tree was wholy <hi>without us.</hi> That great <hi>multitude</hi> of whom <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Rev. 7.14.</note> are ſaid to have <hi>waſhed their</hi> (own) <hi>Robes, and made them white in the Blood of the Lamb.</hi> This intimates a Believers betaking of himſelf, and <hi>flying for refuge</hi> to the ſatisfaction of Jeſus Chriſt; for till then, ſin is not <hi>actually</hi> remitted, nor the preſon juſtified. If this were not a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary <hi>antecedent qualification</hi> for Actual forgiveneſs, how is it to be underſtood, that God hath <hi>ſet forth</hi> Chriſt <hi>to be a propitiation through faith in his Blood?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.25.</note> And that <hi>we are juſtified by Faith?</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 5.1.</note> We are therefore commanded to <hi>draw near</hi> to God,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.22.</note> 
               <hi>having our Hearts ſprinkled from an evil conſcience; i.e.</hi> not only having a pardon <hi>procur'd</hi> and prepar'd <hi>for</hi> us by Chriſt, but <hi>brought home to</hi> us by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:132881:22"/>believing in him. And the Blood of Jeſus thus <hi>apprehended</hi> and laid hold of by Faith, is called the <hi>Blood of ſprinkling.</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 12.24.</note> Hence it is, that we read of our being <hi>Elected through the ſprinkling of the Blood of Jeſus Christ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.2.</note> as a <hi>means</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>end</hi> of Election. It is one of the excellent Characters given to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.28.</note> that <hi>by faith he kept the Paſſeover, and ſprinkling of Bolld.</hi> For after the Sacrifices were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, he <hi>took of the Blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 24.8.</note> 
               <hi>and ſprinkled it upon the people. David</hi> very plainly alludes to this in that famous <hi>Penitential Paſalm;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſal 31.7.</note> 
               <hi>Purge me with Hyſſop, and I ſhall be clean;</hi> becauſe <hi>that</hi> was uſed by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment in the <hi>cleanſing of the Leper,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit. 24.47.</note> to <hi>ſprinkle the Blood upon him.</hi> All this ſignifies the <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar exerciſes</hi> and actings of Faith upon Chriſt as the <hi>Lamb ſlain;</hi> and ſo our <hi>waſhing of Justificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is compleated.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:132881:22"/>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> There is a <hi>waſhing of Sanctification,</hi> which is alſo the work of Chriſt.<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>This is he</hi> (ſays the <hi>Beloved Biſciple</hi>) <hi>whocame by water, as well as by blood.</hi> A lively <hi>Emblem</hi> whereof, was the <hi>water which came out with the Blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 19.34.</note> when the Souldier pierc'd his <hi>ſide</hi> with a Spear. Therefore the Prophet deſcribes him by a <hi>Fountain opened to the Houſe of David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zech. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>and to the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem for ſin and for unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> He cleanſes us not only from our <hi>Guilt,</hi> but from our <hi>Corruption</hi> too. This he does <hi>principally</hi> by his Spirit, and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strumentally</hi> by his Word, and Providences.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Chriſts <hi>waſhing</hi> of us, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> as it reſpects <hi>Sanctification,</hi> is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally performed by the <hi>Spirit.</hi> It was promiſed under the Old Teſtament;<note place="margin">Ezek. 36.25.</note> 
               <hi>Then will I ſprinkle
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:132881:23"/>water upon you,</hi> &amp;c. This is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly interpreted in the New Teſtament,<note place="margin">Joh. 7.33, 39.</note> of the <hi>Effuſion</hi> of the Spirit. He is the great <hi>Operator</hi> employed by our Lord Jeſus in the purifying of defiled Souls. <hi>According to his mercy he ſaved us by the waſhing of Regeneration,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>and renewing of the Holy Ghost; which he ſhed on us abundantly through Jeſus Christ our Saviour. Nature,</hi> in its preſent depraved ſtate, neither can, nor will ever <hi>purge it ſelf. Solomons</hi> Challenge is not to be anſwer'd;<note place="margin">Prov. 20.9.</note> 
               <hi>Who can ſay, I have made my heart clean?</hi> He that firſt <hi>made the heart,</hi> muſt now <hi>make it clean.</hi> We are no more able to be <hi>our own Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers,</hi> than our own <hi>Creators;</hi> for this is <hi>ſuch a kind</hi> of work.<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.10.</note> 
               <hi>Create in me a clean heart, oh God;</hi> was <hi>Davids</hi> earneſt requeſt after his Fall.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.2.</note> It was the <hi>Spirits moving
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:132881:23"/>upon the face of the waters,</hi> which produc'd this <hi>beautiful</hi> World; 'Tis the <hi>influence</hi> of the ſame Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which muſt produce an <hi>holy Comelineſs</hi> in us.<note place="margin">Job. 26.13.</note> God <hi>by his Spirit garniſht the</hi> vifible <hi>Heavens;</hi> and Chriſt by his Spirit muſt <hi>fit us to inhabit</hi> the Inviſible. Nor does the <hi>Merit</hi> of Chriſts bloud appear more in our forgiveneſs, than its <hi>vertue</hi> and <hi>efficacy</hi> does in our renovation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Chriſt <hi>waſhes</hi> us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally by his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Providences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By his <hi>Word.</hi> This is a <hi>Divine Inſtrument</hi> conſecrated by a Divine Authority to this very purpoſe.<note place="margin">Pſul. 12.6.</note> The <hi>words of the Lord are</hi> not onely <hi>pure words</hi> in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but are often <hi>bleſt</hi> and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded for the <hi>working of purity</hi> in us. So our Lord tells his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:132881:24"/>ſciples:<note place="margin">Joh. 15.3.</note> 
               <hi>Now ye are clean through the word that I have ſpoken unto you;</hi> he does not onely tell them, that they were <hi>clean,</hi> but by <hi>what means</hi> they came to be ſo. Thus the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, that Chriſt <hi>gave himſelf for the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.25, 26.</note> 
               <hi>that he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water by the word.</hi> Two great Truths are evidently contained in this Text; 1. That our <hi>Sanctification</hi> is the <hi>price of Blood.</hi> Our <hi>Living to God,</hi> is the effect of Chriſts <hi>dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for us;</hi> if he had not <hi>given himſelf,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> had not been <hi>given.</hi> 2. That the <hi>word</hi> of Chriſt is ordinarily made uſe of by him in the <hi>cleanſing</hi> of thoſe whom he deſigns to ſave. It hath his <hi>ſpecial Inſtitution</hi> for this end; theſe <hi>waters of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> are the <hi>pool</hi> which we muſt come to, and where we muſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:132881:24"/>wait to be heal'd of our <hi>Impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> This is <hi>Gods way</hi> for the <hi>cleanſing of our own way.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.9.</note> Not that there is any cleanſing force or power in the <hi>meer Letter</hi> of the Scriptures, or in the <hi>ſound</hi> of Preaching: but as it is a <hi>proper means</hi> to deal with reaſonable Creatures by (therefore choſen by Chriſt's Infinite <hi>Wiſdom</hi>) and as it is accompanied with the <hi>mighty workings</hi> of the Eternal Spirit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Our waſhing is perform'd Inſtrumentally by his <hi>Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;</hi> eſpecially by <hi>Afflictive</hi> ones. For indeed <hi>Proſperity</hi> does oftner <hi>ſully</hi> and <hi>pollute,</hi> than help to <hi>make us clean.</hi> It is the Mercy and Goodneſs of Chriſt to order our troubles ſo, that they <hi>ſhall not overwhelm,</hi> and yet that they <hi>ſhall purge</hi> us.<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.6.</note> 
               <hi>Surely in the flouds of great waters, they ſhall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:132881:25"/>not come nigh</hi> unto us; but ſo much as will nappily tend to <hi>waſh away our filth,</hi> ſhall not be <hi>kept back</hi> from us.<note place="margin">Dan. 11.35.</note> 
               <hi>Some of them of underſtanding</hi> (ſays the Prophet) <hi>ſhall fall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 33.</note> (viz. <hi>by the ſword and flame, and captivity and ſpoil,</hi> as we may gather from what goes before) <hi>to try them, and to purge, and to make them white.</hi> Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings will have no ſuch ſucceſs upon <hi>Reprobates</hi> indeed; <hi>the wicked will do wickedly</hi> ſtill;<note place="margin">c. 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>and not underſtand;</hi> they will <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue</hi> ſinning (and perhaps <hi>ſin more,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 28.22.</note> like <hi>Ahaz</hi>) <hi>in the time of their diſtreſs; Swine,</hi> if <hi>plung'd</hi> never ſo oft into the <hi>water,</hi> will retain their <hi>filthy Nature,</hi> and return again after all, to <hi>wallow in the mire.</hi> But Afflictions to all the Elect of God, are <hi>ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied means</hi> for the removal of <hi>Sin,</hi> and increaſe of <hi>Grace;</hi> though
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:132881:25"/>they are not the <hi>chaſtiſements of our peace,</hi> yet they have a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to make us <hi>partakers of Gods Holineſs.</hi> They do not <hi>purchaſe our Reconciliation,</hi> but they <hi>promote our Sanctification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Third</hi> thing, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> is to prove the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of this waſhing, in order to our being Partakers with Chriſt. Now though <hi>that</hi> waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Chriſt, which referrs to <hi>Juſtification</hi> be abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to our Participation with him, (for every one to whom the ſatisfaction of Chriſt is <hi>not applied,</hi> muſt needs be in an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardoned</hi> ſtate, and every one in ſuch a ſtate, muſt needs be <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated</hi> from Chriſt both here, and for ever; He <hi>glorifies</hi> none,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> but <hi>whom he juſtifies</hi> before-hand) Yet 'tis the waſhing of <hi>Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which I ſhall chiefly ſpeak
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:132881:26"/>to; becauſe the Luſts of men too frequently tempt them to believe, that they may be in an <hi>unholy, polluted</hi> ſtate, and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>have fellowſhip</hi> with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Scripture ſayes as much (one would think) as can be ſaid, for the rooting out of this perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious miſtake, if men would but ceaſe <hi>hearkening to Satan more than unto God.</hi> Our Lord deals very Plainly and poſitively with <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus</hi> in this caſe;<note place="margin">Joh. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>Except a man be born of water, and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the kingdom of God.</hi> The <hi>New birth</hi> here is oppoſed to the <hi>Natural;</hi> as we are <hi>born into the World,</hi> of Earthly Parents,<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.6.</note> 
               <hi>we are in our blood,</hi> when we are <hi>born again</hi> through the power of the Spirit, we <hi>are born of Water,</hi> to ſignifie our <hi>cleanſing</hi> from our <hi>former filth;</hi> and this muſt be, or elſe the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:132881:26"/>
               <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> where Chriſt is, will be <hi>ſhut</hi> againſt us. So the <hi>Apoſtle:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>If any man have not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi> By the ſame <hi>price,</hi> that Chriſt <hi>purchas'd Heaven</hi> for us hereafter, he <hi>purchas'd the Spirit</hi> for us here: that by being <hi>made like</hi> to him now, we might be fitted to <hi>enjoy</hi> him at laſt. As Chriſt is our <hi>way</hi> to the Father, ſo the work of the Spirit muſt warrant and <hi>Evidence our Title</hi> to Chriſt; we have manifeſtly no Intereſt <hi>in him,</hi> till the Spirit hath wrought Holineſs <hi>in us.</hi> Once more, the <hi>ſame Apoſtle</hi> ſays;<note place="margin">Cor. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>If a man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature.</hi> We muſt be the <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip to God in Christ,</hi> or 'tis impoſſible that we ſhould have any <hi>Right</hi> or <hi>Relation</hi> to him. If the <hi>Old man</hi> be ſtill alive in us, whereby Heart and Life are both
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:132881:27"/>corrupted, we have nothing to do with the <hi>ſecond Adam.</hi> Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the perſon of the <hi>Redeemer</hi> does neceſſarily ſuppoſe the work of a <hi>New Creation.</hi> We can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have any <hi>inheritance</hi> with Chriſt <hi>as brethren,</hi> unleſs our <hi>Fathers Image</hi> be reſtor'd upon us. Many other Teſtimonies might be produced to the ſame purpoſe; But the particular <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> of the Indiſpenſible neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>ſuch</hi> waſhing by Chriſt, in order to partaking with him, are theſe which follow.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As Jeſus Chriſt is a <hi>ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Head,</hi> he cannot be link't with any other than <hi>Holy Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi> That <hi>Body,</hi> of which he is the Head, muſt be <hi>conformable</hi> to him. An <hi>Head of ſuch fine Gold</hi> will not be joyn'd (as the Head in <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s <hi>Image</hi> was)
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:132881:27"/>to <hi>miry feet of Clay.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.15.</note> The <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of an Harlot</hi> cannot be the <hi>Members of Chriſt. Dead</hi> and <hi>fruitleſs Branches which are in</hi> Chriſt by viſible profeſſion, <hi>are taken away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 15.2.</note> becauſe Chriſt is a <hi>living and fruitful Vine.</hi> To <hi>ſay that we have fellowſhip with him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 1.6, 7.</note> when <hi>we walk in darkneſs,</hi> muſt needs be <hi>a lye,</hi> becauſe <hi>he is in the light.</hi> Our bleſſed Lord will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver conſent to be <hi>matcht</hi> with any that are <hi>unſuitable</hi> to himſelf; (though he muſt with thoſe that are <hi>inferiour,</hi> or elſe with <hi>none.</hi>) If the <hi>'Bridegroom</hi> be <hi>fairer than the children of men,</hi> the <hi>Spouſe</hi> is to be <hi>beautified through his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> alſo. <hi>Incongruous mixtures,</hi> and <hi>un-natural conjunctions</hi> were forbidden under the Law;<note place="margin">Deut. 22.9, 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſow thy Vineyard with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſeeds,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nor plow with an Oxe and an Aſs together. Nor
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:132881:28"/>wear a garment of divers ſorts,</hi> &amp;c. The things forbidden here, were not <hi>evil in themſelves,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>meaning</hi> and deſign of God in giving ſuch Laws to the People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> was to ſhew, how <hi>hateful</hi> the <hi>mingling</hi> of thoſe things in Religion would be, which had no <hi>ſimilitude</hi> or <hi>agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in their nature. Believers alſo in the New Teſtament are charg'd (though it be not ſo carefully attended to, as it ought) that they ſhould not <hi>unequally yoke themſelves with unbelievers;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14.</note> Do we think then that <hi>Chriſt will be yoked with</hi> Belial?<note place="margin">v. 15.</note> If the <hi>ſons of God</hi> ſhould not unite them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the <hi>Daughters of Men,</hi> can we ſuppoſe that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous</hi> will incorporate with thoſe which are <hi>unſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:132881:28"/>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As Chriſt is an <hi>holy Lord,</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> he muſt maintain and keep up the hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of an <hi>holy Government.</hi> He muſt not loſe the <hi>Glory</hi> of being a <hi>Prince,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 5.31.</note> while we enjoy the <hi>benefit</hi> of his being a <hi>Saviour.</hi> He is appointed to <hi>rule</hi> every one whom he <hi>redeems,</hi> and to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe his <hi>Governing power</hi> at the ſame time with his <hi>ſaving mercy.</hi> He <hi>came not to deſtroy the Law,</hi> but to <hi>fulfil it perfectly</hi> himſelf, and to ſee it <hi>ſincerely fulfill'd</hi> by us. He muſt <hi>diſinherit</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecters of hsi <hi>commands,</hi> from <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Promiſes;</hi> and if he inveſts us with the <hi>righteouſneſs of Faith,</hi> 'tis neceſſary that he ſhould expect from us the <hi>Duties of Obedience. David,</hi> an holy Prince,<note place="margin">Pſ. 101.4.</note> reſolv'd that he <hi>would not know</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> not tolerate or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:132881:29"/>
               <hi>a wicked perſon;</hi> and can we imagine, that our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus will fall ſhort of his <hi>Type,</hi> and ſhelter the workers of iniquity <hi>under his wing,</hi> or give <hi>protection</hi> to thoſe that renounce his <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion?</hi> It becomes a <hi>good Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> to make his <hi>beſt Subjects,</hi> his <hi>onely Favorites;</hi> and ſhall the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> be worſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd than the <hi>Kingdoms of Men?</hi> Is not <hi>the Scepter of his Kingdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>a Scepter of Righteouſneſs?</hi> and muſt he turn it into a <hi>Rod of Wickedneſs,</hi> by gratifying the Luſts of thoſe that would be a blemiſh and <hi>reproach</hi> to him? Surely Chriſt will not <hi>proſtitute</hi> his own Name and dignity, as he is <hi>exalted</hi> to be a <hi>King;</hi> nor ſo far give up that <hi>Office,</hi> as to lay them <hi>in his boſom,</hi> who tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple his Laws <hi>under foot.</hi> He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuffer a <hi>contempt of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:132881:29"/>in thoſe that are <hi>partakers of his Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As Chriſt is the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator</hi> of an <hi>Holy Covenant,</hi> he muſt look after, and require a performance of the <hi>neceſſary terms.</hi> God and Man are the two <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> in the Covenant; he mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates between both, and engages as a <hi>Surety</hi> for both. He under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes not onely for God's <hi>Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation</hi> to us, but for our <hi>return</hi> to God; if there be a failure on one part, there can be no accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of the other; if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main <hi>impenitent,</hi> God muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main <hi>implacable,</hi> and Chriſt's Suretiſhip will be of no uſe or advantage to us. His great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the World was to confirm the <hi>Covenant with many: i.e.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 9.27.</note> the New Covenant, which though it be not ſtrictly a <hi>Covenant of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:132881:30"/>Works,</hi> yet works are not <hi>altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> excluded by it; Works are thruſt out from being the <hi>merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious condition</hi> of our bleſſedneſs, but they are taken in as a <hi>needful qualification</hi> for it. The <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> does oblige us to all holy <hi>ſervices,</hi> as well as aſſure us of a glorious <hi>Salvation;</hi> it tends to deliver us from being <hi>ſlaves to ſin,</hi> as well as from being <hi>Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in Hell.</hi> It is manifeſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we continue under the <hi>Old Covenant,</hi> while we are <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purged from our old ſins;</hi> when we are brought into the bond of the <hi>New Covenant,</hi> God does infuſe <hi>new frames</hi> and diſpoſitions itno us. A ſinner in his filth, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently a <hi>ſtranger to this Covenant;</hi> we may gather thus much from what God ſays by the <hi>Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 16.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>I ſware unto thee, and entred into a Covenant with thee,</hi> (a Covenant
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:132881:30"/>different from <hi>that</hi> at firſt) <hi>&amp;c. Then waſhed I thee with water, yea I throughtly waſht away thy bloud from thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>Sin hath dominion</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thoſe that are <hi>under the Law,</hi> but not over ſuch as are <hi>under Grace.</hi> So that Chriſts <hi>ratifying</hi> of the ſecond Covenant, makes Sanctification neceſſary to our partaking with him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> As Chriſt muſt <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> us to an <hi>holy God,</hi> it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that he ſhould firſt make us an <hi>holy people.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> muſt be <hi>ſanctified</hi> and cleans'd by Grace,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.27.</note> that it may be <hi>preſented a Glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch thing, but holy and without blemiſh.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this <hi>act</hi> of Chriſt, the <hi>Preſentation of Souls</hi> to God, the Scripture ſpeaks in ſeveral places. <hi>To preſent you holy, and unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1.22.</note>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:132881:31"/>
               <hi>and unreprovable in his</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> in the Fathers) <hi>ſight.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 24.</note> 
               <hi>To him that is able — to preſent you fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs before the preſence of his Glory, with exceeding joy.</hi> This is done more <hi>privately</hi> and particularly at our <hi>Death;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.7</note> for then <hi>the ſpirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns unto God that gave it;</hi> and Jeſus Chriſt ſends his <hi>Angels</hi> to <hi>convey</hi> the Soul from Earth to Heaven, where at its <hi>arrival,</hi> he immediately preſents it unto God. 'Tis done more <hi>publickly</hi> and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly at the <hi>End of the World,</hi> when there ſhall be a <hi>General Aſſembly</hi> of Chriſtsſanctified ones; then Chriſt will ſtand at the <hi>head of his whole flock,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2.13.</note> and ſay to God, <hi>Here am I and the children which thou haſt given me.</hi> Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>as Redeemer</hi> (which is <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate</hi> unto Gods, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>diſtinct</hi> from it) was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to continue no longer
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:132881:31"/>than <hi>this world,</hi> when the <hi>world to come</hi> takes place, His Kingdom is to be <hi>delivered up,</hi> and his <hi>fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> to his truſt muſt be <hi>accounted for;</hi> and therefore all the Souls wherewith he was <hi>entruſted</hi> by the Father, are to be <hi>preſented</hi> to him: the Father <hi>gave them to him,</hi> and when he hath finiſhed his work upon them, he muſt <hi>give them back to the Father.</hi> Now, can we think, that a God, who is <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in Holineſs,</hi> will receive us, if we are defiled by Sin? Will he that <hi>loves Righteouſneſs,</hi> accept of thoſe that are <hi>far from Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs?</hi> Will he <hi>acquit</hi> his Son in the execution of his Office, if ſo great a branch of it, is the <hi>waſhing</hi> us from our filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, be <hi>neglected</hi> and undone?</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:132881:32"/>
            <p>Fifthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> As Chriſt is no lodge us in an <hi>holy place,</hi> he muſt <hi>fit</hi> us by Holineſs to be the <hi>Inhabitants.</hi> One of the ends of his <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> was thus expreſs't by himſelf; <hi>I go to prepare a place for you;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 14.2.</note> but the work of Chriſt would be no more than half done, if he did not ſend his <hi>Spirit</hi> in his ſtead, <hi>to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare us for that place.</hi> Our Lord <hi>purchaſt</hi> an Inheritance for us by his <hi>Death,</hi> he went to take <hi>poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of it for us, when he <hi>aſcended upon high;</hi> And is it not after all as neceſſary now, that we ſhould be <hi>made meet for his Inheritance?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Veſſels of Wrath</hi> are <hi>fitted for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> before they are puniſh with it; and muſt not the <hi>Veſſel of Mercy</hi> be <hi>prepared unto Glory</hi> before they are advanc't to it?<note place="margin">Rom. 9.22, 23.</note> What an <hi>Hell</hi> would <hi>Heaven</hi> be to thoſe that <hi>rejoyce in Iniquity</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:132881:32"/>and <hi>have pleaſure in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> What a <hi>Priſon</hi> would <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe</hi> be to thoſe that <hi>love to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi> What delight could the <hi>Old man</hi> take in the <hi>New Jern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem?</hi> The Souls of the Unſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, are now the <hi>Habitation of unclean ſpirits;</hi> what <hi>agreement</hi> therefore can be hereafter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, and the <hi>habitation of Gods Holineſs?</hi> How unfit muſt we be to <hi>dwell in the preſence</hi> of God at laſt, unleſs we are made living and <hi>ſacred Temples</hi> for God to dwell in here? The Holy Ghoſt hath put this <hi>bar</hi> upon the <hi>Gate of the City;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel. 21.27.</note> 
               <hi>There ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fileth.</hi> Angels were <hi>expelled</hi> out of it, aſſoon as they ſinned; can we then ſuppoſe, that God will take up ſinners from hence, and <hi>admit</hi> them into it? It is ſtyled Gods <hi>holy Heaven;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 20.6.</note> 'tis his peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:132881:33"/>Palace and <hi>Throne,</hi> which he will not have <hi>ſtain'd by the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach</hi> of any uncleanſed Soul. The purity of that <hi>State,</hi> does call for anſwerable purity in <hi>us.</hi> There is a neceſſity of being <hi>undefiled in the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 119.1.</note> if we would be <hi>bleſſed in the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> and laſt thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> was the <hi>Application of</hi> the whole. A double Uſe may be made of this point, by infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch <hi>Truths,</hi> and perſwading to ſuch <hi>Duties,</hi> as naturally flow from it.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>improvement</hi> we may make of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ƲSE </seg>1</label> is by way of <hi>lnformation,</hi> as to ſeveral Truths, reſulting thence.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> From hence we may learn, wherein the <hi>great evil</hi> and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:132881:33"/>miſchief of <hi>ſin</hi> lyes. It hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bad effects, even in this Life, and with reſpect to the concerns of this Life; but the <hi>worſt of all</hi> is, that it <hi>defiles the Soul.</hi> This is that which <hi>fools make a mock at,</hi> and which common ſinners think moſt ſlightly of; but this is that which is of the moſt fatal ruining conſequence. This is that which calls for ſuch a valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and effectual <hi>expiation;</hi> this is that which calls for the <hi>pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the ſoul</hi> of Chriſt in our ſtead, and the <hi>pouring out of the ſpirit</hi> of Chriſt upon us. The <hi>neceſſity</hi> of Chriſts waſhing every one that hath part with him, is an undeniable <hi>convincing proof</hi> of the loathſome filthineſs which is in ſin. Otherwiſe we might cry as the <hi>Diſciples</hi> did, when the <hi>Ointment was pour'd</hi> on their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters head,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.8.</note> 
               <hi>To what purpoſe is this
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:132881:34"/>waſt?</hi> Why might not our Lord Jeſus have ſpared this <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>coſt,</hi> and left us in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, wherein he found us? Certainly, he was at a vaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence and trouble to waſh us <hi>in vain,</hi> if fin had not greatly pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted and deprav'd us? It would do well therefore, if we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber'd this, and laid it to heart, that in every act of wickedneſs, we make work for the <hi>fire of Hell,</hi> or the <hi>bloud of God: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming</hi> by the one, or <hi>purging</hi> by the other, muſt be the iſſue of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> This plainly ſhews, that the <hi>defiling effects</hi> of ſin have extended to <hi>all mankind.</hi> The Doctrine of Souls being waſht by Chriſt, does ſuppoſe that we are <hi>univerſally</hi> in a corrupt ſtate If any man were <hi>born clean,</hi> that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:132881:34"/>man might have part with Chriſt, though he were never waſht. We may eaſily infer from this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary act of the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> what miſery was brought upon us by the <hi>firſt.</hi> The very <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> were ſenſible, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times complain'd, of the Souls being <hi>out of frame,</hi> but they knew not diſtinctly, <hi>what</hi> this diſorder was, nor <hi>how</hi> it muſt be <hi>remedyed.</hi> If we had not loſt the <hi>amiable purity</hi> which we were once becautified with, and if there did not an <hi>heap of dirt</hi> appear in the place of that <hi>diſſolved ſnew,</hi> why ſhould even the <hi>Saints</hi> of God (who are brought out of a <hi>ſtate</hi> of ſin, though afflicted with the <hi>remnants</hi> of ſin) cry out ſo often of their <hi>wretchedneſs?</hi> And indeed, if the ſame Scripture which gives us an account of our <hi>primitive Creation,</hi> did not alſo
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:132881:35"/>report the means and manner of our <hi>fall,</hi> it would not be credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that mankind could have <hi>ſo degenerated.</hi> As there are the <hi>ſeeds of all diſtempers</hi> in our <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> at the time of our birth, ſo the <hi>principles of all manner of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption</hi> in our <hi>hearts</hi> by nature. No part is free from the infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but the <hi>Leproſie covers our whole skin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit. 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>from the head to the foot, whereſoever we look</hi> What Jeſus Chriſt hath done for our Healing and Cleanſing, does lead us to the humble conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this <hi>General Plague.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> This teaches us the <hi>Inſufficiency</hi> of the Legal Sacrifices and the <hi>reaſon</hi> of their Ceſſation <hi>He</hi> (i.e. the <hi>Meſſiah</hi>) <hi>ſhall cauſe the Sacrifice and Oblation to ceaſe</hi> Chriſt by his Death took <hi>them</hi> away,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.27.</note> becauſe they <hi>could not take
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:132881:35"/>away ſin.</hi> They were weak and unprofitable, inſignificant and worthleſs <hi>in themſelves,</hi> only as they typified and <hi>repreſented the Blood of the Lamb,</hi> which was to be actually ſlain in the fullneſs of time.<note place="margin">Heb. 9.13.</note> What could <hi>the Blood of Bulls and Goats, and the Aſhes of an Heifer ſprinkling the unclean,</hi> do more, than <hi>purifie the fleſh?</hi> How could ſuch <hi>carnal Ordinances</hi> have any vertue for the removing of <hi>Spiritual defilements?</hi> God therefore impos'd them only <hi>for a time,</hi> and when his Son had <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled the end</hi> of them, he <hi>put an end to them.</hi> Nay, even while they were enjoyn'd and us'd, the <hi>Imperfection</hi> of them was plainly intimated by their frequent <hi>repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition;</hi> if they could have <hi>purg'd the Conſcience from ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 10.2.</note> they needed only to have been <hi>offered once.</hi> Chriſt dyed but <hi>once,</hi> and that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:132881:36"/>once dying was <hi>enough;</hi> he hath thereby <hi>perfected for ever them that are ſanctified;</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">v. </seg>4</label> And we read of <hi>this act</hi> of waſhing his Diſciples feet <hi>but once;</hi> once for all, to ſhew that what the yearly and dayly Offerings under the Law <hi>could not do,</hi> his one offering <hi>did.</hi> The reaſon of their <hi>preſcription</hi> and <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> in the Jewiſh Church ſo long, was their being <hi>ſigures</hi> of the Sacrifice of Chriſt; the reaſon of their <hi>abrogation</hi> at laſt; was <hi>their</hi> real invalidity, and <hi>his</hi> full per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, This Diſcovers to us the falſhood of the <hi>Doctrine of Penance</hi> in the <hi>Romiſh Church.</hi> This Text is evidence enough that the Refuge of <hi>Humane Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> which Sinners in <hi>their Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> fly to, is indeed a <hi>Pefuge of Lyes. If [I] waſh thee not,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:132881:36"/>'tis <hi>proper to</hi> Chriſt, and not <hi>poſſible</hi> to any Creature, to waſh a Soul from the <hi>ſmalleſt ſin.</hi> Men may inflict what they pleaſe upon themſelves, and uſe the utmoſt <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities</hi> to their fleſh, but it will be no advantage to them in this caſe; the greateſt of <hi>voluntary ſufferings</hi> avails nothing as to the purging of the leaſt tranſgreſſion; the tormenting of our <hi>bodies</hi> can never put away the ſin of our <hi>ſouls.</hi> It muſt be <hi>puret blood</hi> than ours, that <hi>makes us clean.</hi> Poor deluded Creatures commonly <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe</hi> their guilt by ſuch practiſes, but they cannot <hi>leſſen</hi> it; they <hi>whip</hi> and <hi>lance</hi> themſelves (it may be,) and think by that means to be rid of ſome of their pollution, but this makes them rather <hi>greater ſinners</hi> than they were before. It is therefore a piece of folly and madneſs, like <hi>his</hi> in the Goſpel,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:132881:37"/>who being poſſeſt with an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>ran among the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Tombs, crying and cutting himſelf with ſtones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiſthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> We may gather from hence, that the moſt ſincere <hi>Evangelical Repentance</hi> makes no <hi>compenſation</hi> to God for Sin: The beſt <hi>Penitent</hi> in the World, if his <hi>head were Waters,</hi> and his <hi>eyes a fountain of tears,</hi> would not be able to <hi>waſh himſelf</hi> How can the largeſt <hi>floods</hi> of godly ſorrow <hi>blot out</hi> ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity from Gods <hi>book,</hi> or remove the <hi>ſtain</hi> which is ſo <hi>deep</hi> in our own Conſciences? Suppoſe, that we do <hi>bring forth fruits meet for Repentanee</hi> in a Life of <hi>new Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> for the time to come, what is this, as to the expiating of <hi>ſins that are paſt?</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obj.</note> Yes; perhaps ſome may ſay, the Holy Ghoſt aſſures us,<note place="margin">Prov. 16.6.</note> that <hi>By Mercy and Truth Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qity
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:132881:37"/>quity is purged.</hi> To this, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, 1.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> We may very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe words to hold forth the <hi>Mercy and Truthof God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cartwr.</hi> in locum.</note> So the <hi>ſame Expreſſions</hi> muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, not only in ſeveral other places, but in the <hi>ſame Book. Mercy and Truth ſhall be to them that deviſe good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">c. 14.22.</note> And therefore it ſeems to be meant only of Gods Mercy in <hi>promiſing,</hi> and his Truth in <hi>performing;</hi> his <hi>free Grace</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> to his own word. The <hi>ſcope</hi> of that whole verſe appears in this ſhort <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe</hi> upon it; <q rend="inline">God out of his meer benignity, agreeable to his ſtanding Revelation, does purge the ſins of Men, that they for the future being reſtrain'd by an holy fear, may not return to them.</q> 2. If we ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it of Mercy and Truth <hi>in us,</hi> the ſence of it amounts to no
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:132881:38"/>more than this, that <hi>True Faith working by Love</hi> is the <hi>means</hi> of <hi>purifying the heart</hi> through the blood of Chriſt. It purges Sin, not by its <hi>its own power,</hi> but the efficacy of its <hi>Object,</hi> our Lord Jeſus. Our Faith hath an <hi>alloy</hi> of Unbelief, and our Repentings a <hi>mixture</hi> of Sin, which require a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgation for <hi>themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Another Inference from the main Doctrine may be, that the <hi>waſhing of Water</hi> in <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> is no ſufficient ſecurity, that we ſhall <hi>partake with Chriſt. He ſhall baptize you</hi> (ſays his <hi>forerun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>) <hi>with the Holy Ghoſt, and with Fire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.11.</note> Multitudes come under <hi>that Ordinance,</hi> who know not what <hi>this</hi> means, and yet without <hi>this</hi> our participation with Chriſt is <hi>impoſſible.</hi> I cannot but conclude,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:132881:38"/>that the <hi>wide door</hi> of <hi>Baptiſmal Regeneration</hi> hath <hi>let in</hi> vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Souls <hi>to Hell.</hi> Men being taught to elieve, that when they are <hi>Baptized,</hi> they are certainly <hi>Regenerate, and born again,</hi> they reſt contented, and look no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells us plainly, how <hi>Baptiſm ſaves;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>not</hi> (as it is) <hi>the putting away of the filth of the fleſh, but</hi> (as it is atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with an holy reſtipulation, or) <hi>the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God.</hi> It is not the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adminiſtration</hi> of the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of Water, but <hi>inward opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Spirit and <hi>application</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt, which makes a ſinner clean. What do we think of that woful Impoſtor, <hi>Simon Magus?</hi> After he was <hi>baptized,</hi> he yet remained <hi>in the gall of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs, and in the bond of Iniquity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 8.13 <hi>with</hi> 23.</note> The ſame may be <hi>perceived,</hi> and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:132881:39"/>pronounc'd of thouſands beſides, upon as notorious grounds, as it was of him. Why ſhould <hi>this Sacrament</hi> be more conſtantly and infallibly accompanied with <hi>clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Grace,</hi> than that <hi>other Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Supper,</hi> which <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites</hi> many times partake of, and the <hi>Devil enters into them</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with greater force?</p>
            <p>Seventhly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> It is eaſie to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect from hence, that Jeſus Chriſt is not <hi>meerly the Pattern</hi> of our Purification, but <hi>alſo the Author.</hi> It is very <hi>true,</hi> that He is the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of it; therefore we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to <hi>purifie our ſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>even as he is pure;</hi> but this is not the <hi>whole truth,</hi> nor the <hi>principal part.</hi> The entire Myſtery is ſet forth in thoſe words of the <hi>Apoſtle;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>He ſuffered for us, leaving us an Example,</hi> &amp;c. Indeed Chriſt <hi>in ſuffering</hi> left us
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:132881:39"/>an Example, but his great end was to ſuffer <hi>for us; i.e.</hi> in our room and ſtead, as our <hi>Subſtitute</hi> and Surety, as one that <hi>repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> us, ſuffering that which was <hi>due to us,</hi> and which if he had not, we muſt have born <hi>our ſelves.</hi> I condemn none for magnifying the <hi>Example of Chriſt,</hi> but I muſt declare an abhorrence of, and enter a caution againſt, that <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinian fallacy</hi> and cheat, which would ſubvert the Goſpel under this pretence. Chriſt does not does not waſh us, by being a Pattern of abſolute purity <hi>in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> but by the applying of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>to us,</hi> and the workings of his Grace <hi>in us.</hi> The <hi>benefit of his Example</hi> would be utterly loſt, and come to nothing, if his <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſin,</hi> and <hi>dying for ſin</hi> were not accepted by God as the juſt and valuable price of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:132881:40"/>
            <p>Eighthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> This warrants us to infer, that thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> which come up to the <hi>highest degree of Reformation,</hi> are the moſt likely to <hi>ſhare in the glory of the latter dayes.</hi> Theſe Days are in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial and peculiar manner called <hi>Chriſt's Times.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.15.</note> Then his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will be moſt <hi>eminently</hi> ſet up, and he ſhall <hi>take to himſelf his great Power and Reign,</hi> ſubduing all that make oppoſition to him The queſtion now it, who ſhall <hi>partake with him</hi> to this kind of <hi>Heaven upon Earth?</hi> Whom will the <hi>King of Saints delight to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> in thoſe times, which will be ſo glorious? I think, I may very ſafely Anſwer; Thoſe that are <hi>counted the filth of the World</hi> but in truth are moſt <hi>purged from it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt a few names ever i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sardis</hi> (ſays Chriſt to <hi>that Church</hi> or the Church in <hi>that period
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:132881:40"/>which hav not defiled their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and they ſhall walk with me in white, for they are worthy.</hi> Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with Chriſt <hi>in white,</hi> does note a proſperous and flouriſhing State, (as on the contrary, a ſad and doleful State is often ſignified by <hi>covering with blackneſs,</hi> and <hi>clothing in Sackcloth,</hi>) and they who have taken care to <hi>keep their garments unſpotted,</hi> are the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whom Chriſt will reckon worthy of <hi>Communion with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> in this State. Who are the <hi>Hundred and forty four thouſand that ſtand with the Lamb upon Mount Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">c 14.1.</note> but ſuch as are <hi>not defiled with Women,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">v. </seg>4</label> (<hi>i.e.</hi> have had nothing to do with the <hi>Mother of Harlots</hi>) and ſuch as <hi>are without fault?</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> have not partaken of <hi>Babylons ſins.</hi>) Some of the <hi>terms of reproach</hi> in this Generation will <hi>become Characters of honourable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:132881:41"/>and marks of renown, when Chriſt <hi>comes in his</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected) <hi>Kingdom;</hi> for his Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Methods of <hi>Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> will not be as Mens are. When the <hi>Lord dwells in Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joel 3. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations</hi> muſt be carried on to an higher pitch, and he <hi>will cleanſe what he hath not yet cleanſed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 4.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>He that remaineth then in Jeruſalem, ſhall</hi> (with more reaſon) <hi>be called holy,</hi> becauſe the remainder of our <hi>ſilth will be waſht away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second <hi>Improvement</hi> of this Point, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ƲSE </seg>2</label> may be by way of <hi>Exhortation,</hi> to thoſe Duties, which ſhould be learnt from it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Labour to be <hi>deeply ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> of your defiled <hi>Natures</hi> and <hi>Lives.</hi> Till we are brought to a ſerious acknowledgment of this, we are not <hi>fit</hi> to be waſht, tho'
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:132881:41"/>we <hi>need</hi> it. <hi>If we confeſs our ſins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 John 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>he is faithful and juſt to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs.</hi> The faithfulneſs of God does not bind him to <hi>cleanſe</hi> us from that which we will not <hi>confeſs. David</hi> bewails his <hi>ſecret faults</hi> (as well as thoſe that were <hi>known</hi> and open) and prays for <hi>cleanſing from them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.12.</note> He who is <hi>pure in his own eyes,</hi> ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue <hi>filthy ſtill.</hi> Till we come to <hi>ſee</hi> our own <hi>Leprous Faces,</hi> and thereupon to <hi>loathour ſelves,</hi> there is no hope of our being clean. Methinks that Challenge which God put to the Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſhould affect every one, and ſtrike us with confuſion. <hi>How canſt thou ſay, I am not polluted?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 2.23.</note> Unleſs this ſelf-juſtifying <hi>Mouth be ſtopt,</hi> the <hi>Fountain</hi> which God hath <hi>opened,</hi> will be <hi>ſealed up</hi> againſt us.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:132881:42"/>
            <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Addreſs</hi> your ſelves to Chriſt with ſincertity and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency, that he may <hi>waſh</hi> you, both <hi>within</hi> and <hi>without.</hi> He <hi>offers</hi> this priviledge to you in the <hi>Word,</hi> go you and <hi>urge</hi> it to him in <hi>Prayer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 13. <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> He ſays, <hi>Wilt thou not be made clean?</hi> Plead, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulate with him, in his own Language? <hi>Lord, wilt thou not make me clean? When ſhall it on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be?</hi> When ſhall I <hi>liſt up my fact to thee without ſpot,</hi> and by that means, without <hi>ſhame?</hi> He is able both to <hi>convince</hi> you of your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs, and <hi>cure</hi> you too; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he hath <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> to ſay,<note place="margin">Luk. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>I will, be thou clean;</hi> and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> many promiſes upon record ſpeak his <hi>readineſs</hi> and <hi>inclination</hi> You may feel a little <hi>ſmart</hi> and pain, while he is about thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> work;<note place="margin">Mal. 3.2.</note> for the <hi>Prophet</hi> compare him to <hi>Fullers Soap,</hi> which will
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:132881:42"/>
               <hi>ſearch</hi> in order to cleanſing: But remember, how much more tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable this is,<note place="margin">Mark 9.49.</note> than to be <hi>ſalted with fire.</hi> One of theſe two muſt be; if your <hi>filthineſs be not purged,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 24.13.</note> 
               <hi>fury will</hi> unavoidably <hi>reſt upon</hi> you. And therefore do not act the <hi>Hypocrites</hi> part, in getting the <hi>outſide</hi> only <hi>clean,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.25.</note> like thoſe <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> to whom <hi>the greater damnation</hi> is threatned. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">v. </seg>14</label> Be hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily willing to <hi>lay aſide all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 1.21.</note> if you do not ſo, you do not ſo, you do nothing. If every performance do not proceed <hi>out of a pure heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.5.</note> the <hi>end of the Commandment</hi> is not anſwer'd. You only <hi>mock God,</hi> and <hi>deceive your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Live to Chriſt</hi> in the Exerciſe of <hi>pure and undefiled Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> and take heed <hi>of falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the dirt again.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.20.</note> It is ſad to be <hi>entangled in the pollutions of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:132881:43"/>World,</hi> after we have <hi>eſcapt them through the knowledge of Chriſt.</hi> Walk with all poſſible exactneſs and <hi>circumſpection,</hi> and ſay, as the <hi>Spouſe</hi> did to a worſe purpoſe, (whenever the Tempter aſſaults you) <hi>I have waſhed my feet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Song. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>how ſhall I defile them?</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">My Saviour hath cleanſed me from my ſins by his own Blood, I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fore go and ſin no more.</q> Upon this account <hi>ſtoop</hi> not too much to the <hi>filthy puddles</hi> of Creature-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments; Converſe more with <hi>things above,</hi> where Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is. Remember, that he by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>to purifie you to himſelf.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2.14.</note> Your purgation by ſo dear a remedy, was to make you <hi>meet for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters uſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.21.</note> and not to leave you at <hi>Satans</hi> diſpoſal, by a ſinful grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the <hi>fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:132881:43"/>
            <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Improve the <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of Life</hi> for your <hi>increaſe in Holineſs.</hi> The <hi>beſt ground</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires frequent <hi>culture;</hi> and they that are <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> want <hi>more purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> ſtill. Therefore it is,<note place="margin">Joh. 15.2.</note> that God does not <hi>immediately</hi> upon our Converſion, <hi>take us out of the World,</hi> and ſnatch us into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; but orders us to abide here for a while, that we may be <hi>yet better prepar'd</hi> for his everlaſting Preſence. God does not uſe to perfect ſo great a change, <hi>in a moment,</hi> or in the <hi>twinckling of an Eye,</hi> (though perhaps he may do it <hi>ſometimes,</hi> for the Exaltation of his Soveraignty.) Luſts are <hi>gradually</hi> mortified, before they are <hi>totally</hi> extingniſh't, For this reaſon, we are yet <hi>ſojourning</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Farth; becauſe we are to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ain <hi>further,</hi> before we come to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:132881:44"/>our <hi>Journey's End. Death</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd, becauſe the <hi>work of life</hi> is not done, nor the <hi>deſign</hi> of it ſufficiently accompliſht. Theſe are the <hi>days of our Purification;</hi> when they are over, our Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication will commence. Be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent then <hi>in this your day,</hi> (like thoſe under the <hi>Law,</hi> that were to <hi>waſh their clothes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 19.19.</note> 
               <hi>and bathe themſelves in water</hi>) and for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſuch diligence, you <hi>ſhall be clean at even.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Get your <hi>holy Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,</hi> and <hi>earthly Comforts</hi> waſht by Chriſt alſo. There is a <hi>dung</hi> in our Duties,<note place="margin">Mal. 2.3.</note> which he muſt ſeparate them from, or elſe they will not be acceptable to God. When there were ſome that mentioned to an <hi>Eminent perſon</hi> on his Death-bed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> G. H.</note> a piece of Service which he had done,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:132881:44"/>he anſwerd piouſly, <hi>It is a good work, if it be ſprinkled with the bloud of Chriſt.</hi> Even the <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> of the Righteous (as well as of the <hi>wicked</hi>) would be <hi>an abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord,</hi> if it were not for the more grateful, and <hi>unblemiſh'd</hi> Sacrifice of his Son. Bring all your offerings therefore to this <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> that God may <hi>receive</hi> them from his <hi>hands,</hi> perfum'd with his <hi>Incenſe.</hi> All that we would have the Father to <hi>approve,</hi> we muſt have him to <hi>recommend.</hi> And there is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a <hi>ploouting vanity</hi> in Worldly things, which will be miſchievous to us, if Chriſt do not remove it by his Spirit; how miſerable are they, to whom <hi>nothing is pure!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1.15.</note> and how happy they on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide,<note place="margin">Luk. 11.41.</note> to whom <hi>all things are clean!</hi> Let it then be your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eigned deſire, that you may not
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:132881:45"/>
               <hi>poſſeſs</hi> any thing in this Life, which will tend to unqualify or <hi>indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> you for the next. <hi>Sanctified wants</hi> and ſtraits are ten thouſand times better, than the moſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful <hi>corrupted Enjoyments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> You, who have had <hi>Experience</hi> of this waſhing by Chriſt, <hi>fear not</hi> the Devil's <hi>fouleſt Accuſations.</hi> He may <hi>beſpatter</hi> you, but he cannot <hi>hurt</hi> you; he hath nothing to <hi>do with</hi> you, whatever he <hi>ſays againſt</hi> you. Why then ſhould you ſlaviſhly dread ſuch a diſarmed Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Why ſhould you ſtand in tormenting awe of him, who muſt neceſſarily <hi>fall before you?</hi> His <hi>Weapons</hi> (his chiefeſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the very ſinews and <hi>ſtrength of his cauſe</hi>) wherein <hi>he truſted,</hi> are now gone, and he ſhall never be permitted to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:132881:45"/>them. While you were in an unpurified ſtate, he could al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a great deal of <hi>truth</hi> for your Condemnation; but now he muſt be forc'd to make uſe of <hi>Calumny,</hi> and that cannot be to your prejudice. You have the <hi>favourable word</hi> of Chriſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and vindicate you, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he may dare to aſperſe you; <hi>He that is waſhed</hi> (ſays our Lord to his <hi>Diſciples</hi> in this Chapter) <hi>is clean every whit.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">ver. </seg>10</label> All comfort is wrapt up in the aſſurance of this, notwithſtanding your <hi>daily ſlips,</hi> and Satan's <hi>malicious devices.</hi> Be encouraged, as <hi>David</hi> was, in that prayer to God;<note place="margin">Pſal. 65.3.</note> 
               <hi>Iniquities prevail againſt me,</hi> (yet) <hi>as for our tranſgreſſions, thou ſhalt purge them away.</hi> Deſpiſe the <hi>Enemy that reproaches</hi> you, and conſider what a powerful Friend you have to confront and <hi>rebuke</hi> him. It
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:132881:46"/>is the happineſs, and ought to be the ſupport, of Believers, that though they may be <hi>blackned</hi> by their <hi>Helliſh Accuſer,</hi> they ſhall be <hi>clear'd</hi> by their <hi>Heavenly Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:132881:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Books Printed for and Sold by <hi>John Salusbury,</hi> at the Riſing <hi>Sun</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Written by the ſame Author.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. THE Duty and Support of Believers in Life and Death.</item>
               <item>2. The Period of Humane Life determined by the Divine Will.</item>
               <item>3. The Uſefulneſs of Spiritual Wiſdom, with a Temporal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</item>
               <item>4. The mighty Wonders of a Merciful Providence; in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preach'd on the Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving-Day, <hi>Jan.</hi> 31. 1688/89.</item>
               <item>5. The Churches Plea for the Divine Preſence to proſper Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb facs="tcp:132881:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>Force; in a Sermon preacht on the Faſt-Day, <hi>Jun.</hi> 5, 1689.</item>
               <item>6. The Excellency of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Faith, as to its Objects and Supports; in a Sermon preach'd, <hi>Nov.</hi> 5. 1689.</item>
            </list>
            <p>A Rational Defence of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity, wherein the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice oſ Non-conformiſts is vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated from promoting Popery, and ruining the Church; imput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them by Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> in his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation.</hi> Alſo his Arguments from the Principles and way of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers and firſt Diſſenters are anſwered, and the Caſe of the preſent Separation truly ſtated and the blame of it laid where it ought to be, and the way to Union among Proteſtants is poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at. By <hi>Gilbert Rule,</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>A Guide to the practical Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician,
<pb facs="tcp:132881:47"/>ſhewing from the moſt Authors, both Ancient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern the trueſt and ſafeſt way of curing all Diſeaſes. Publiſhed in Latin by the Learned Dr. <hi>Theoph. Bonet,</hi> Phyſitian at <hi>Geneva,</hi> and now rendered into <hi>Engliſh</hi> with an Addition of many conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Caſes and Excellent Medicines for every Diſeaſe. Collected from Dr. <hi>Waltherus</hi> his <hi>Sylva Medica</hi> by one of the Colledge of Phyſicians, <hi>London.</hi> To which is added the Office of a Phyſician and perfect Tables of every diſtemper, and of any thing elſe conſiderable.</p>
            <p>The true Propheſies or Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtications of <hi>Michael Noſtrada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> Phyſician to <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d. <hi>Frances</hi> 2d. and <hi>Charles</hi> the 9th. Kings of <hi>France</hi> and one of the beſt Aſtronomers that ever were. A Work full of Curioſity and Learning.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:132881:48"/>
            <p>The Conformiſts Charity to Diſſenters, and Concurrence with the Favour granted them in the Act for Toleration; proved from the Works of the moſt Eminent Divines of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Several Arguments humbly propoſed for Conceſſions and Alterations in the Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and in the Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in order to a comprehenſion by a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Pattern of the Divine Temple Sanctuary, and City of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> meaſured ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Ezekiels</hi> laſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Viſion, <hi>Chap.</hi> 49. to the end. Deſigned as a Preface to two late Treatiſes, <hi>viz.</hi> the Prophetick Hiſtory of the Reformation till the great Re-reformation, and the grand Apocaliptical Viſion of
<pb facs="tcp:132881:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Witneſſes, Riſing and Aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; which ſhall contemperate with this Temple opened in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at the ſame 1697. By <hi>Tho. Beverly,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>A new Examination of <hi>Lilly</hi>'s Grammar in <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> in Twelves.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of Marriage; To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with ſome remarks on the Marriage of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebecca.</hi> In Twelves.</p>
            <p>The Portraicture of a Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtian, with an Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of Mans Creation.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
